Register of the M. T. (Mikhail Trofimovich) Zarochentsev Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
M. T. (Mikhail Trofimovich) Zarochentsev papers
1910-1959
2001C52
Hoover Institution Archives
7 microfilm reels (1.1 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, patents, business records, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the meat and fish refrigeration industries.
Zarochentsev, M. T. (Mikhail Trofimovich), b. 1879
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
M. T. Zarochentsev, a prominent specialist in refrigeration, was born on 18 September 1879. His career in refrigeration engineering began even before graduation from the Institute of Transportation in Moscow in 1909. He participated in the work of the International Congresses of Refrigeration in Paris (1908), Vienna (1910), London (1924), and Rome (1928), and was one of the founders of the Russian Refrigeration Association. Editor of a scientific periodical on refrigeration in Russia, he also authored numerous books on the subject, such as Kholodil'noe dielo (Moscow, 1911), Kholod v plodovodstvie (Simferopol', 1911), and Ledniki (Moscow, 1912).
During the First World War, as consultant to the Ministries of Agriculture and Transportation, he oversaw the construction of numerous packing houses, cold storage facilities, and thousands of refrigerated railway cars. Following the Revolution, he spent two years in France before becoming general manager of the Estonian packing house A/S Külmetus from 1922 to 1927. Continuing scientific work on refrigeration in France and Great Britain in 1928-1930, he saw that without larger capital investment than that available in Europe, his plans would remain unrealizable. In 1931 he proceeded to America to interest investors in what would become known as the Z process of quick freezing. As vice-president of the American Z Corporation, and an official of Z-Pack Corporation and National Frosted Foods Sales Corporation, Zarochentsev became one of the leading figures in refrigeration into the early 1950s, when he retired.
Chronology
1879 September 18 Born, Stavropol', Russia
1907 Graduated, Institut putei soobshcheniia, Moscow, Russia
1910 Graduated, Moskovskii kommercheskii institut, Moscow, Russia
1911 Author, Kholodil'noe dielo
1912 Author, Ledniki
1922-1927 General Manager, A/S "Külmetus"
1930 Author, Between Two Oceans
1932 Founder, American Z Corporation
Scope and Content Note
Mikhail Trofimovich Zarochentsev (Zarotschenzeff) was a specialist in meat and fish refrigeration, a prolific inventor in the field and holder of a number of patents on methods of quick-freezing. The CAREER FILE contains information related to Zarochentsev's scientific work (notes, reports and calculations) and business activities, including his meat-packing operations: A/S "Külmetus"(Estonia), American Z Corporation, National Frosted Foods Sales Corp. and Z-Pack Corporation. It also includes articles, notes, patents, and promotional materials relating to the "Z" process of quick-freezing and related refrigeration issues.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
Engineers.; Fishery products--Preservation.; Meat--Preservation.; Russia.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1918-1959 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Calling cards, clippings, curriculum vitae, diploma, membership certificates, receipts, and subject file, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1943-1950 and undated (Box 1)
  Card and letters, arranged alphabetically by correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1910-1957 (Box 1-3)
  Articles, interviews, and scrapbook, arranged chronologically by title
- Career File, 1912-1950 (Box 4-7)
  Business records, patents, scientific notes and subject file, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Subject File, 1927-1948 (Box 7)
  Brochures and clippings, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Printed Matter, 1914-1951 (Box 8-9)
  Primarily works on refrigeration, food processing, fox breeding, and meat- and fish-packing not directly related to Zarochentsev or his work. Not filmed
- Photographs, 1929-1951 (Box 10)
  Albums and loose prints depicting Zarochentsev, frozen foods and food processing operations, places he visited and various individuals. Not filmed
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1918-1959 (Box 1)
  General note
  See also CAREER FILE for materials relating to Z's professional activities in this field
  - Calling cards (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings (Folder 1: 2)
  - Curriculum vitae (Folder 1: 3)
  - Diploma (Folder 1: 4)
  - Membership certificates (Folder 1: 5)
  - Receipts (Folder 1: 6)
  - Subject file
    - Jubilee of, 1949 May 7
      - General. (Folder 1: 7)
        Includes clippings, poems and speeches read at the jubilee celebration
      - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Folder 1: 8)
        Letters of congratulation
      - Scrapbooks (Folder 1: 9)
    - Voloshin, A. (Folder 1: 10)
      Correspondence and clippings relating to his conflict with Zarochentsev
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1943-1950 and undated
  See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Subject file for correspondence relating to Zarochentsev's jubilee and conflict with A. Voloshin
  - General, 1943-1947 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
  - Kotomkin, Aleksandr, 1949-1950 (Folder 1: 12)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1910-1957
  See also CAREER FILE for scientific notes and business reports and promotional materials, and scientific reports and patents
  - General
    - Interviews, 1933-1950 (Folder 1: 13)
      Includes articles citing Z's words and opinions
    - Scrapbook. (Folder 1: 14)
      Includes primarily clippings of newspaper articles and some typescripts
    - Volume of Zarochentsev's pre-Revolutionary books, articles, and reports to scientific congresses. (Box-folder 2: 1)
      Includes Kholodil'noe dielo (Moscow, 1911), Kholod v plodovodstvie (Simferopol', 1911), Ledniki (Moscow, 1912), and other works
  - "Kholodil'noe delo, ego printsipy i znachenie,", n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
    Holograph
  - "Nasha pishcha, n.d. (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Tatianin den'," Novaia zaria (Folder 2: 4)
    Printed copy
  - "Tekhnika khraneniia i perevozki baraniny," and "Osnovnye voprosy kommercheskoi eksploatatsii kholodnykh skladov," Trudy VI-go s'iezda po kholodil'nomu dielu v Moskvie, 1913 (Folder 2: 5)
    Printed copy (includes entire conference proceedings)
  - Kholod - drug cheloveka," public lecture, 1925 October 15 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Typescript. Includes advertisements and programs for the lecture from 1932 to 1951
  - "Precooling Stations in Russia," Refrigerating World, 1927 October (Folder 3: 2)
  - "Chilling in Bacon Factories," Ice and Cold Storage, 1927 December-1928 January (Folder 3: 3)
  - "Schnellkühlprozess geschlachteter Schweine bei der Herstellung von Bacon," Zeitschrift für Eis- und Kälte-Industrie, 1928 (Folder 3: 4)
  - "Congélation rapide de viande et de poisson à l'entrepôt frigorifique de Paris-Vaugirard," Et des industries frigorifiques, 1929 February-March (Folder 3: 5)
  - Between Two Oceans, 1930 (Folder 3: 6)
    Promotional leaflet
  - "Quick Freezing of Various Meat Cuts and Edible Offals," Meat Trades' Journal, 1930 April 17 (Folder 3: 7)
  - "Rapid Chilling and Freezing of Fish and Meat in Atomised Brine," Ice and Cold Storage, 1930 August (Folder 3: 8)
  - "Latest Achievements in Rapid Freezing and Chilling Methods," paper read before a meeting of the British Association of Refrigeration, at the Hall of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Storey's Gate, Westminster, S.W., England, 1930 December 4 (Folder 3: 9)
    Printed copy and abstract from proceedings
  - "Conservation of Fish on Trawlers," The Fish Trades Gazette, 1931 April 25 (Folder 3: 10)
  - "Preservation of Fish on Trawlers," The Fish Trades Gazette, 1931 June 27 (Folder 3: 11)
  - "Quick-Freezing Opening New Perspectives in the Fish Industry," paper presented at the International Fisheries Congress, Paris, France, 1931 July 20-25 (Folder 3: 12)
    Typescript
  - "Dry and Wet Freezing in the Meat Industry," Ice and Refrigeration, 1932 February (Folder 3: 13)
  - "Neues vom 'Z'-Schnellgefrier-Verfahren in Amerika," Die Kälte-Industrie, 1932 November (Folder 3: 14)
  - "The Z Process on Packaged Food Manufacturing," Ice and Refrigeration, 1932 November (Folder 3: 15)
  - "Quick Freezing Abroad," letter to the editor, Refrigeration, 1933 July (Folder 3: 16)
  - "Refrigeration of Fish in Newfoundland," Refrigeration, 1933 October (Folder 3: 17)
  - "Preservation of Poultry," Refrigerating Engineering, 1933 December (Folder 3: 18)
  - "Quick Freezing Poultry," The National Provisioner, 1933 December 9 (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Fischgefrieranlage nach dem 'Z'-Verfahren," Die Kälte-Industrie, 1934 (Folder 3: 20)
  - "Refrigeration of Fish in Newfoundland," Cold Storage and Produce Review, 1934 February 15 (Folder 3: 21)
  - "Problems in Quick Freezing of Spinach," Ice and Refrigeration, 1934 March (Folder 3: 22)
  - "Fish Freezing Advances in Newfoundland," Fishing Gazette, 1934 July (Folder 3: 23)
  - "Old Problems in the Fishing Industry and New Ways of Solving Them," Ice and Refrigeration, 1934 October (Folder 3: 24)
  - "El Sistema 'Z' en Norteamerica," Industrias pesqueras, 1934 December 15 (Folder 3: 25)
  - "Want to Be Van Winkle? Try Freezing Process," Rochester Democrat and Chronicle, 1935 August 18 (Folder 3: 26)
  - "The Practical Application of Refrigeration in the Fishing Industry," Refrigeration and Air Conditioning, 1935 September (Folder 3: 27)
  - "The Quick Freezing and Marketing of Ducks," Ice and Refrigeration, 1936 July (Folder 3: 28)
  - "Advances in Quick-Freezing During Past Four Years," Distribution and Warehousing, 1936 September (Folder 3: 29)
  - "Four Years Progress in Quick-Freezing," Ice and Refrigeration, 1936 September (Folder 3: 30)
  - "Schnellgefrieranlage für Enten in Amerika," Die Kälte-Industrie, 1936 September (Folder 3: 31)
  - "How 'Z' Quick-Freezing Process Is Used By the Long Island Duck Industry," Refrigeration News, 1936 September 2 (Folder 3: 32)
  - "Quick Freezing in England," Quick Frozen Foods, 1938 August 1 (Folder 3: 33)
  - "Quick Frozen Foods for the World Armies," Quick Frozen Foods, 1938 October 15 (Folder 3: 34)
  - "World Wide Development of Quick Freezing," Quick Frozen Foods, 1938 December 15 (Folder 3: 35)
  - "Frosted Foods Today: Where Do We Go From Here?" Fishing Gazette, 1939 February (Folder 3: 36)
  - "How Quick Frozen Foods Came Into Being - And Stayed," Quick Frozen Foods, 1939 February 15 (Folder 3: 37)
  - "The Altek System of Refrigerated Transport in Europe," Ice and Refrigeration, 1939 April-May (Folder 3: 38)
  - "Quick Freezing Shows Progress in Foreign Fisheries," Quick Frozen Foods, 1939 May 15 (Folder 3: 39)
  - "Quick-Frozen Meat Supplies: Efficient Distribution for the Forces and Civilian Population," Modern Refrigeration, 1939 December 21 (Folder 3: 40)
  - "'Flexible Froster' Experiments," American Egg and Poultry Review, 1940 March (Folder 3: 41)
  - "New Plan for Wartime Meat Handling," The National Provisioner, 1940 March 30 (Folder 3: 42)
  - "Frosted Foods in the Ice and Cold Storage Industry," Ice and Refrigeration, 1941 February (Folder 3: 43)
  - "Sovremennoe miasnoe snabzhenie armii i naseleniia,"., 1941 December 2 (Folder 3: 44)
  - "Ot Labradora do Ognennoi zemli,"., 1942 February 1 (Folder 3: 45)
  - "La congelación rapida en el progreso argentino," Revista argentina del frio, 1942 May-June (Folder 3: 46)
  - "Cutting Patagonian Lamb," Butcher's Advocate, 1942 September 9 (Folder 3: 47)
  - "Quick Freezing Lamb in Tierra del Fuego," The National Provisioner, 1942 September 12 (Folder 3: 48)
  - "South America Looms Big as Seafood Production Source," Fishing Gazette, 1942 November (Folder 3: 49)
  - "Quick Freezing," Butcher's Advocate, 1943 January 6 (Folder 3: 50)
  - "Quick Freezing of Meats in South America," Refrigerating Engineering, 1943 August (Folder 3: 51)
  - "Sovremennoe polozhenie sushki pishchevykh produktov v S. Sh. Severnoi Ameriki,"., 1943 October 15 (Folder 3: 52)
  - "Will Argentine Imports Spur Quick Freezing in the U.S.?" Meat, 1944 January (Folder 3: 53)
  - "Sterilization of Meat By Electronic Heating," Quick Frozen Foods, 1944 May-June (Folder 3: 54)
  - "Will Dielectric Heating Pave the Way for South American Meat?" Meat, 1944 December (Folder 3: 55)
  - "Nasha pishcha segodnia i posle voiny," Novaia zaria, 1945 August 7-8 (Folder 3: 56)
  - "Quality Control: A 1946 Problem," Frosted Food Field, 1946 January (Folder 3: 57)
  - "Aeromobil'," Novaia zaria, 1946 January 10 (Folder 3: 58)
  - "Frozen Berries in Alaska," Western Frozen Foods, 1947 January (Folder 3: 59)
  - "Posledniaia para liudei na zemle," Novaia zaria, 1948 January 23-27 (Folder 3: 60)
  - "Fingalova peshchera," Novaia zaria, 1948 January 28 (Folder 3: 61)
    Printed copy. Includes English translation
  - "Sud'ba cheloveka,"., 1948 February 24 (Folder 3: 62)
    Holograph. Includes background materials
  - Fakty moei zhizni," Novaia zaria, 1949 May 18-28 (Folder 3: 63)
  - "Iubilei V. G. Mamul'ian," Novaia zaria, 1949 September 22 (Folder 3: 64)
  - "Bud'te dobry," Novaia zaria, 1951 March 16 (Folder 3: 65)
  - "Revoliutsiia na kukhne," Novaia zaria, 1957 May 7 (Folder 3: 66)
  - "Desiat' zapovedei morali," Novaia zaria, 1957 June 19 (Folder 3: 67)
- CAREER FILE, 1912-1950 (Box 4)
  See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS for articles on refrigeration and food processing
  Includes scientific notes and business-related interviews and promotional materials authored by M. T. and W. M. Zarochentsev.
  - General, 1935-1944 (Folder 4: 1)
    Includes articles about or mentioning Zarochentsev and son and their discoveries, inventions and business activities, and scientific memoranda and reports
  - Business records, 1926-1950
    - A/S "Külmetus."
      Includes reports of the general manager (Zarochentsev), clippings, correspondence, instructions, regulations, and price lists
      - Undated (Folder 4: 2)
      - 1926 (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1927 (Folder 4: 4)
    - American Z Corporation, 1929-1942 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
      Also known as International Z Corporation
    - National Frosted Foods Sales Corp., 1938-1950 (Folder 5: 3)
      Includes articles by Zarochentsev's son, W. M. Zee, correspondence, and promotional materials
    - Z-Pack Corporation, 1936-1938 (Folder 5: 4)
      Includes brochures, clippings, and promotional materials
  - Patents, 1923-1939
    Patents on methods and equipment for freezing food products, arranged alphabetically by author
    - A-C (Folder 5: 5)
    - D-S (Folder 5: 6)
    - T-Z (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Zarochentsev. (Folder 6: 2)
      Includes patents and lists of those applied for and granted, as well as diagrams of refrigeration equipment
  - Scientific notes, 1931-1935 and undated
    - General. (Folder 6: 3)
      Calculations, diagrams, notes and sketches
    - "Z" Process. (Folder 6: 4-5)
      For its implementation and industrial use, as well as for articles about it, see American Z Corporation
  - Subject file - Refrigeration. (Folder 7: 2-5)
    Includes articles by W. M. Zarochentsev and issues of Quick Frozen Foods, on whose advisory board M. T. Zarochentsev served
- SUBJECT FILE, 1927-1948
  - Avak the Healer (Folder 7: 6)
  - Communism (Folder 7: 7)
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' (Folder 7: 8)
  - Miscellany (Folder 7: 9)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1914-1951 (Box 8-9)
  Not filmed.
  Primarily works on refrigeration, food processing, fox breeding, and meat- and fish-packing not directly related to Zarochentsev or his work
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1929-1951 (Box 10)
  Albums and loose prints depicting Zarochentsev, frozen foods and food processing operations, places he visited and various individuals
  - Albums (Folder 10: 1)
  - Loose prints
    - Zarochentsev, M. T. (Folder 10: 2)
    - Altek refrigerated freight cars (Folder 10: 3)
    - Frigorifico Conference, 1944 (Folder 10: 4)
    - Frozen foods (Folder 10: 5)
    - Rio de Janeiro, Brazil (Folder 10: 6)
    - Sao Paolo, Brazil (Folder 10: 7)
    - Miscellany (Folder 10: 8)